<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Teachings | Chandra N. Jack, PhD</title>
    <link>/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/</link>
      <atom:link href="/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Teachings</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Chandra Jack 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/chandra-jack.netlify.app/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Teachings</title>
      <link>/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversity Statement</title>
      <link>/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/diversity_statement/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/diversity_statement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Representation matters. Having role models and mentors that students can identify with matters. This is not to say that students from underrepresented backgrounds cannot receive excellent mentoring from white faculty members because I did. My undergraduate mentor is the reason I remained in science. However, as an African American woman and a first-generation college student, I can’t help but wonder if navigating academia as a student would have been easier if I had STEM professors that looked like me. If I had someone to tell me that imposter syndrome was real. If I didn’t have a professor that was unsympathetic to the difficulty of trying to balance the need for studying with needing to work to pay for school. The STEM pipeline is leaky today not necessarily because of specific barriers but because of the disproportionate effect of those barriers, especially when multiplied across the effects of race, gender, socio-economic status, disability status, and LGBTIQ+ identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recognize the obstacles that underrepresented students contend with from my experiences. It is why I am so committed towards increasing diversity in higher education and making STEM a more supportive environment. I organized and led a sandbox session on diversity and inclusion in two years (2017 and 2018) at the annual meeting for the BEACON Center for the Study of Evolution in Action. These sessions used small group activities and invited open discussions about the implicit biases that individuals face from society at large and how that translates to barriers preventing underrepresented groups from feeling welcomed and staying in science. Each year, 25-30 participants at career stages ranging from undergraduates through full professors attended these sandboxes. My work helped BEACON work towards their goals of increasing diversity and combatting implicit biases. As a postdoc at Rice (2012-2013), I served as a postdoctoral liaison for the Council on Diversity and Inclusion&amp;rsquo;s (CODI&amp;rsquo;s) Graduate Life Committee to help implement the Graduate African Americans and Latinos Merging with American Indians for Action (GALMA) initiative. While serving on this committee I gave presentations about changing research directions after gaining a PhD and fellowship opportunities and met with prospective students designed to recruit and retain underrepresented students. My activities with GALMA helped to expand the STEM pipeline and improved the campus climate for African American, Latino, and Native American students across the Rice campus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also extensively mentored students throughout my career, with a focus on mentoring students from under-represented groups. I have mentored 33 students: six African Americans, five Hispanics, one American Indian, three students with disabilities, and twenty-three women. Two of my students received GRFP funding; two students, both underrepresented minority women, won awards for best undergraduate researcher in Rice’s EEB department; one woman switched to a science major; seven of my students  were co-authors on my papers; five students went onto advanced degrees, and another three are working towards them. My experiences are framed by the mentoring I received as a student and it changed my life for the better. Increasing diversity has been a guiding principle of my life that I look forward to continuing with future students.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Student mentoring</title>
      <link>/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/student_mentoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/student_mentoring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the students that I have mentored as a postdoc and PhD student. They are all amazing and I am so proud of what they accomplished in the lab and are continuing to accomplish.&lt;/p&gt;






  



  
  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/chandra-jack.netlify.app/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/student_mentoring/Picture1_hu1ea412cdfc47603e2fcb71291c852dc9_922356_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;/chandra-jack.netlify.app/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/student_mentoring/Picture1_hu1ea412cdfc47603e2fcb71291c852dc9_922356_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;960&#34; height=&#34;597&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;







  



  
  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/chandra-jack.netlify.app/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/student_mentoring/Picture2_hu90264753ea12963dfb66b5060ae52941_286361_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;/chandra-jack.netlify.app/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/student_mentoring/Picture2_hu90264753ea12963dfb66b5060ae52941_286361_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;960&#34; height=&#34;540&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;







  



  
  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/chandra-jack.netlify.app/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/student_mentoring/Picture4_hu130d838b8c7b0efd5ff0ba5daca3211c_122065_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;/chandra-jack.netlify.app/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/student_mentoring/Picture4_hu130d838b8c7b0efd5ff0ba5daca3211c_122065_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;607&#34; height=&#34;317&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;







  



  
  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/chandra-jack.netlify.app/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/student_mentoring/Picture5_hue38dc894cde007f65f23df7364dd8c31_801311_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;/chandra-jack.netlify.app/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/student_mentoring/Picture5_hue38dc894cde007f65f23df7364dd8c31_801311_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;901&#34; height=&#34;650&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;







  



  
  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/chandra-jack.netlify.app/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/student_mentoring/Picture6_hu2d5964e1305e759e85b4eda55a8e1c20_787683_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;/chandra-jack.netlify.app/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/student_mentoring/Picture6_hu2d5964e1305e759e85b4eda55a8e1c20_787683_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;960&#34; height=&#34;542&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;







  



  
  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/chandra-jack.netlify.app/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/student_mentoring/Picture7_hu04a2d53caf40b2cb7d1911ffa682bbb5_795643_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;/chandra-jack.netlify.app/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/student_mentoring/Picture7_hu04a2d53caf40b2cb7d1911ffa682bbb5_795643_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;960&#34; height=&#34;540&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Philosophy</title>
      <link>/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/teaching_philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/teaching_philosophy/</guid>
      <description>





  



  
  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/chandra-jack.netlify.app/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/teaching_philosophy/education-614155_1920_huc3d14d05b294fd1743438efb91d9f47b_739722_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;/chandra-jack.netlify.app/chandra-jack.netlify.app/teaching/teaching_philosophy/education-614155_1920_huc3d14d05b294fd1743438efb91d9f47b_739722_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1920&#34; height=&#34;1369&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-good-pedagogy-is-important&#34;&gt;Why good pedagogy is important&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quality of teaching that students receive plays a significant role in the decision to stay in STEM or leave. When I was an undergraduate, it was easy to distinguish between classes that I did not enjoy and those that I did. However, it was not until I began teaching that I was able to identify why I learned better in some classes and why some classes were more enjoyable than others. I realized that I got the most out of those classes where the professors engaged with the students beyond the typical lecture format and there was interaction with other students. It was obvious that these professors were excited about what they were teaching, wanted to share their knowledge with students and had taken the time to develop an environment that was hospitable to different learning styles. Having a well thought-out pedagogy improves student learning and allows them to move from simplistic ways of thinking to incorporate the more complex forms of learning outlined in Bloom&amp;rsquo;s taxonomy. Effective teaching requires consideration of the whole student beyond just their learning style. It necessitates thinking about their background, culture, and life outside of the classroom. Multiple studies have found that the intellectual, social, emotional, and physical environment of a course strongly influences classroom learning (Ambrose, Ch. 6). By deliberately creating an inclusive, welcoming environment in class or the lab, students are more likely to feel as if they belong, and have better learning outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;Boahemaa2.png#floatleft&#34; &gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;Boahemaa2.png#floatleft&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mentoring-experience&#34;&gt;Mentoring Experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the lab I train my students so that they learn every technique that I know and that they are fully engaged in the research. When they first start working in the lab, I start with basic techniques such as preparing media and work up to more complex tasks that are part of the actual experiments. We don’t just go over the protocols of the experiment; we also go over the theory behind it so they know why they are doing a particular experiment and what questions we hope to answer, with the goal of having them take ownership of their projects. As part of this, I have had my students present their work at university symposia and regional meetings and they have been co-authors on several of my publications. I also use the lab as an opportunity to get my students to make connections between the research we are doing with concepts and ideas that are presented outside of the lab.  I want my students to be able to take what I teach them and use it in other aspects of their lives. As a result, two of my students, both underrepresented minority women, won awards for best undergraduate researcher in Rice’s EEB department, two students received GRFP funding, five students went onto advanced degrees, and another three are working towards them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;teaching-experience&#34;&gt;Teaching Experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a PhD student, I helped design a half-semester seminar course (EBIO116) that introduced freshman to ecology and evolutionary biology research at Rice. I chose two papers from EEB labs that we would discuss for one week before getting a tour of the lab. We would meet and talk to researchers at all stages from undergraduate researchers to lab PIs. We finished the course with a field trip to either the Houston Zoo or the Houston Museum of Natural Science to introduce the students to science and research outside of the university setting. The first semester I taught I had three students. The next semester my class grew to fifteen students.
For the last two years at WSU, I have been teaching a data camp program to the REU students in our lab. The first summer that I taught it, I focused on teaching students how to do data science using the statistical program R. Last summer I revamped the course to include an experiential learning component. Prior to the students arriving, I setup a large experiment to study the genotypic effects of different rhizobia on host plant traits and fitness. When the students arrived, they collected data ranging from biomass to flowering time. Then I taught them how to use R to visualize and model data along with some basic statistics. At the end of the program the students developed a testable hypothesis using the data they had collected, analyzed the data, and presented their work at the WSU Summer REU poster session&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-expectations-for-my-students-and-myself&#34;&gt;My expectations for my students and myself&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will continue to develop as a teacher, using informed, research-based pedagogy
I will strive to reach all of my students, no matter their learning style and create an environment where they want to learn and will be able to apply their knowledge outside of the classroom.  My hope is that my students leave my class with a hunger to learn more about the world around them. I know that even if they do not pursue careers in science, they will have gained an appreciation and understanding of science. Additionally, they will have developed important skills in problem solving and critical thinking, which will serve them well, no matter their career choice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
